<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Adolescent on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/adolescent/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Adolescent on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/adolescent/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Criminogenic or Criminalized? Testing an Assumption for Expanding Criminogenic Risk Assessment</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2019/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     OBJECTIVES: Proponents of criminogenic risk assessment have called for its widespread expansion throughout the criminal justice system. Its success in predicting recidivism is taken as evidence that criminogenic risks tap into the causes of criminal behavior, and that targeting these factors can reduce correctional supervision rates and even prevent crime. This study challenges these assertions, by testing the implicit assumption that populations in which recidivism risk factors were identified are interchangeable with populations experiencing the onset/duration of exposure to the criminal justice system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joint Effects of Age, Period, and Cohort on Conduct Problems Among American Adolescents From 1991 Through 2015</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although arrest rates among juveniles have substantially decreased since the 1990s, US national trends in conduct problems are unknown. Population variation in conduct problems would imply changes in the social environment, which would include emergent or receding risk factors. In the present study, we separated age, period, and cohort effects on conduct problems using nationally representative surveys of 375,879 US students conducted annually (1991-2015). The summed score of 7 items measuring the frequency of conduct problems was the outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criminogenic Factors, Psychotic Symptoms, and Incident Arrests among People with Serious Mental Illnesses under Intensive Outpatient Treatment</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although research robustly indicates that general or &amp;quot;criminogenic&amp;quot; factors predict various measures of recidivism, there is controversy about the extent to which these factors, versus untreated symptoms, lead to justice involvement for people with mental illnesses. Based on a sample of 183 people in intensive outpatient treatment followed for an average period of 34.5 months, the present study tested whether criminogenic factors (i.e., factor-analytically derived proxies of some of the &amp;quot;Central Eight&amp;quot;; Andrews &amp;amp; Bonta, 2010) and psychotic symptoms were independently associated with arrest.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
