<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fact Sheets on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fact Sheets on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Visible security measures in schools</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/visible-security-measures-in-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/visible-security-measures-in-schools/</guid>
      <description>Visible Security Measures in Schools: Research Summary     Visible security measures in schools include metal detectors, cameras, and police officers. Nearly 100,000 New York City students walk through airport-style security every day. Ostensibly implemented to increase school safety, critics argue that these measures fail to do so, and instead criminalize students for minor misbehaviors. They see school securitization as part of a broader trend of neoliberal governance to merely manage, rather than repair, the consequences of disinvestment, economic austerity, and unprecedented social inequality in poor and working-class communities, particularly communities of color.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Restorative Practices in Schools: Research Summary</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/restorative-practices-in-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/restorative-practices-in-schools/</guid>
      <description>As an alternative to punitive, zero tolerance policies, restorative practices have been adapted from criminal justice settings to school settings in an effort to keep children in schools and out of the juvenile justice system. The aim of modern restorative practice is to repair harm while preventing further harm through accountability and support. In school settings, restorative practices often involve reconciliation conferencing, mediation, restitution, and/or community service. Early observational studies of restorative practices in schools show reductions in suspensions, expulsions, violence, and disruptive behaviors and improvements in positive relationships and academic achievement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Restorative Practices in Schools: Student Perceptions and Impact on Disparities</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/restorative-practices-in-schools-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/restorative-practices-in-schools-students/</guid>
      <description>The majority of research on restorative practices in schools uses administrative data, particularly data on suspension and expulsion rates, to assess impacts of these practices. However, some studies have surveyed and interviewed students to gain insight into student perceptions of restorative practices. In general, students report improvements in relationships with peers, teachers, and parents; improvements in conflict resolution skills; and reductions in fighting in school.
After participating in school-based restorative practices, students report…     …more positive relationships       A study of a restorative practices program in a middle school in West Oakland found that 91% of students felt the program improved their relationships with other students and 70% felt it improved their relationships with teachers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Restorative Practices in Schools: Faculty and Staff Perceptions</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/restorative-practices-in-schools-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/resources/fact-sheets/restorative-practices-in-schools-teachers/</guid>
      <description>The majority of research on restorative practices in schools has used administrative data, particularly data on suspension and expulsion rates, to assess impacts of these practices. However, some studies have asked school faculty and staff about their perceptions of restorative practices. In general, faculty and staff report improvements in their work environments and school climate, improved relationships with students, and perceived positive outcomes for their students. These findings were captured within specific schools in specific jurisdictions and thus may not be generalizable to different contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
