<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Severity of Illness Index on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/severity-of-illness-index/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Severity of Illness Index on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/severity-of-illness-index/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Criminogenic Factors, Psychotic Symptoms, and Incident Arrests among People with Serious Mental Illnesses under Intensive Outpatient Treatment</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although research robustly indicates that general or &amp;quot;criminogenic&amp;quot; factors predict various measures of recidivism, there is controversy about the extent to which these factors, versus untreated symptoms, lead to justice involvement for people with mental illnesses. Based on a sample of 183 people in intensive outpatient treatment followed for an average period of 34.5 months, the present study tested whether criminogenic factors (i.e., factor-analytically derived proxies of some of the &amp;quot;Central Eight&amp;quot;; Andrews &amp;amp; Bonta, 2010) and psychotic symptoms were independently associated with arrest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Transinstitutionalization Explain the Overrepresentation of People with Serious Mental Illnesses in the Criminal Justice System?</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-does-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-does-2011/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although there is broad consensus that people with serious mental illnesses (SMI) are overrepresented in correctional settings, there is less agreement about the policy trends that may have created this situation. Some researchers and policymakers posit a direct link between deinstitutionalization and increased rates of SMI in jails and prisons, a phenomenon described as transinstitutionalization. Others offer evidence that challenges this hypothesis and suggest that it may be a reductionist explanation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
