<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stigma on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/stigma/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stigma on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/stigma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Structural Stigma and All-Cause Mortality among Sexual Minorities: Differences by Sexual Behavior?</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-structural-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-structural-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Using updated data from the General Social Survey/National Death Index (GSS/NDI) study, we examined whether the relationship between structural stigma-measured by aggregating 4 items assessing prejudice towards homosexuality to the community level-and all-cause mortality is present among gay men/lesbian women. Our hypothesis is based on emerging evidence that indicators of structural stigma specific to homosexuality, such as those used in the GSS/NDI, uniquely predict health outcomes among this group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immigration Policies and Mental Health Morbidity among Latinos: A State-Level Analysis</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-immigration-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-immigration-2017/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     RATIONALE: Despite abundant state-level policy activity in the U.S. related to immigration, no research has examined the mental health impact of the overall policy climate for Latinos, taking into account both inclusionary and exclusionary legislation. OBJECTIVE: To examine associations between the state-level policy climate related to immigration and mental health outcomes among Latinos. METHODS: We created a multi-sectoral policy climate index that included 14 policies in four domains (immigration, race/ethnicity, language, and agricultural worker protections).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
