<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Occupations on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/occupations/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Occupations on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/occupations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Relational Social Class, Self-Rated Health, and Mortality in the United States</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-relational-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-relational-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Applying a relational class theory based on property ownership, authority, and credentials/skill, we analyzed the relationship between class, self-rated health (SRH), and mortality using the 1972–2016 General Social Survey. In a simple measure of class, we assigned respondents to worker, manager, petty bourgeois, or capitalist classes. In a complex measure, we subdivided workers (less-skilled/more-skilled), managers (low/high), and capitalists (small/large). Next, we estimated trends in class structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mental Illness, Drinking, and the Social Division and Structure of Labor in the United States: 2003-2015</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-mental-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-mental-2019/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     BACKGROUND: We draw on a relational theoretical perspective to investigate how the social division and structure of labor are associated with serious and moderate mental illness and binge and heavy drinking.
METHODS: The Panel Study of Income Dynamics and the Occupational Information Network were linked to explore how occupation, the productivity-to-pay gap, unemployment, the gendered division of domestic labor, and factor-analytic and theory-derived dimensions of work are related to mental illness and drinking outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anxious? Depressed? You Might Be Suffering from Capitalism: Contradictory Class Locations and the Prevalence of Depression and Anxiety in the USA</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-anxious-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-anxious-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Despite a well-established social gradient for many mental disorders, there is evidence that individuals near the middle of the social hierarchy suffer higher rates of depression and anxiety than those at the top or bottom. Although prevailing indicators of socioeconomic status (SES) cannot detect or easily explain such patterns, relational theories of social class, which emphasise political-economic processes and dimensions of power, might. We test whether the relational construct of contradictory class location, which embodies aspects of both ownership and labour, can explain this nonlinear pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
