<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sex Factors on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/sex-factors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sex Factors on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/sex-factors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Relational Social Class, Self-Rated Health, and Mortality in the United States</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-relational-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-relational-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Applying a relational class theory based on property ownership, authority, and credentials/skill, we analyzed the relationship between class, self-rated health (SRH), and mortality using the 1972–2016 General Social Survey. In a simple measure of class, we assigned respondents to worker, manager, petty bourgeois, or capitalist classes. In a complex measure, we subdivided workers (less-skilled/more-skilled), managers (low/high), and capitalists (small/large). Next, we estimated trends in class structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joint Effects of Age, Period, and Cohort on Conduct Problems Among American Adolescents From 1991 Through 2015</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although arrest rates among juveniles have substantially decreased since the 1990s, US national trends in conduct problems are unknown. Population variation in conduct problems would imply changes in the social environment, which would include emergent or receding risk factors. In the present study, we separated age, period, and cohort effects on conduct problems using nationally representative surveys of 375,879 US students conducted annually (1991-2015). The summed score of 7 items measuring the frequency of conduct problems was the outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
