<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>conduct disorder on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/conduct-disorder/</link>
    <description>Recent content in conduct disorder on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/conduct-disorder/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Joint Effects of Age, Period, and Cohort on Conduct Problems Among American Adolescents From 1991 Through 2015</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although arrest rates among juveniles have substantially decreased since the 1990s, US national trends in conduct problems are unknown. Population variation in conduct problems would imply changes in the social environment, which would include emergent or receding risk factors. In the present study, we separated age, period, and cohort effects on conduct problems using nationally representative surveys of 375,879 US students conducted annually (1991-2015). The summed score of 7 items measuring the frequency of conduct problems was the outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Psychopathology Matters Most: Identifying Sensitive Periods When within-Person Changes in Conduct, Affective, and Anxiety Problems Are Associated with Male Adolescent Substance Use</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/cerda-when-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/cerda-when-2016/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     BACKGROUND AND AIMS There is a documented link between common psychiatric disorders and substance use in adolescent males. This study addressed two key questions: (1) is there a within-person association between an increase in psychiatric problems and an increase in substance use among adolescent males and (2) are there sensitive periods during male adolescence when such associations are more evident? DESIGN Analysis of longitudinal data collected annually on boys selected randomly from schools based on a comprehensive public school enrollment list from the Pittsburgh Board of Education.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
