<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>neo-Marxist on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/neo-marxist/</link>
    <description>Recent content in neo-Marxist on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/neo-marxist/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Relational Social Class, Self-Rated Health, and Mortality in the United States</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-relational-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-relational-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Applying a relational class theory based on property ownership, authority, and credentials/skill, we analyzed the relationship between class, self-rated health (SRH), and mortality using the 1972–2016 General Social Survey. In a simple measure of class, we assigned respondents to worker, manager, petty bourgeois, or capitalist classes. In a complex measure, we subdivided workers (less-skilled/more-skilled), managers (low/high), and capitalists (small/large). Next, we estimated trends in class structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Decades of Neo-Marxist Class Analysis and Health Inequalities: A Critical Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/muntaner-two-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/muntaner-two-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Most population health researchers conceptualize social class as a set of attributes and material conditions of life of individuals. The empiricist tradition of &amp;lsquo;class as an individual attribute&amp;rsquo; equates class to an &amp;lsquo;observation&amp;rsquo;, precluding the investigation of unobservable social mechanisms. Another consequence of this view of social class is that it cannot be conceptualized, measured, or intervened upon at the meso- or macro levels, being reduced to a personal attribute.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
