<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Female on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/female/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Female on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/female/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mental Illness, Drinking, and the Social Division and Structure of Labor in the United States: 2003-2015</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-mental-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-mental-2019/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     BACKGROUND: We draw on a relational theoretical perspective to investigate how the social division and structure of labor are associated with serious and moderate mental illness and binge and heavy drinking.
METHODS: The Panel Study of Income Dynamics and the Occupational Information Network were linked to explore how occupation, the productivity-to-pay gap, unemployment, the gendered division of domestic labor, and factor-analytic and theory-derived dimensions of work are related to mental illness and drinking outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joint Effects of Age, Period, and Cohort on Conduct Problems Among American Adolescents From 1991 Through 2015</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although arrest rates among juveniles have substantially decreased since the 1990s, US national trends in conduct problems are unknown. Population variation in conduct problems would imply changes in the social environment, which would include emergent or receding risk factors. In the present study, we separated age, period, and cohort effects on conduct problems using nationally representative surveys of 375,879 US students conducted annually (1991-2015). The summed score of 7 items measuring the frequency of conduct problems was the outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immigration Policies and Mental Health Morbidity among Latinos: A State-Level Analysis</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-immigration-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-immigration-2017/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     RATIONALE: Despite abundant state-level policy activity in the U.S. related to immigration, no research has examined the mental health impact of the overall policy climate for Latinos, taking into account both inclusionary and exclusionary legislation. OBJECTIVE: To examine associations between the state-level policy climate related to immigration and mental health outcomes among Latinos. METHODS: We created a multi-sectoral policy climate index that included 14 policies in four domains (immigration, race/ethnicity, language, and agricultural worker protections).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unequal Depression for Equal Work? How the Wage Gap Explains Gendered Disparities in Mood Disorders</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/platt-unequal-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/platt-unequal-2016/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Mood disorders, such as depression and anxiety, are more prevalent among women than men. This disparity may be partially due to the effects of structural gender discrimination in the work force, which acts to perpetuate gender differences in opportunities and resources and may manifest as the gender wage gap. We sought to quantify and operationalize the wage gap in order to explain the gender disparity in depression and anxiety disorders, using data from a 2001-2002 US nationally representative survey of 22,581 working adults ages 30-65.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anxious? Depressed? You Might Be Suffering from Capitalism: Contradictory Class Locations and the Prevalence of Depression and Anxiety in the USA</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-anxious-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-anxious-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Despite a well-established social gradient for many mental disorders, there is evidence that individuals near the middle of the social hierarchy suffer higher rates of depression and anxiety than those at the top or bottom. Although prevailing indicators of socioeconomic status (SES) cannot detect or easily explain such patterns, relational theories of social class, which emphasise political-economic processes and dimensions of power, might. We test whether the relational construct of contradictory class location, which embodies aspects of both ownership and labour, can explain this nonlinear pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criminogenic Factors, Psychotic Symptoms, and Incident Arrests among People with Serious Mental Illnesses under Intensive Outpatient Treatment</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although research robustly indicates that general or &amp;quot;criminogenic&amp;quot; factors predict various measures of recidivism, there is controversy about the extent to which these factors, versus untreated symptoms, lead to justice involvement for people with mental illnesses. Based on a sample of 183 people in intensive outpatient treatment followed for an average period of 34.5 months, the present study tested whether criminogenic factors (i.e., factor-analytically derived proxies of some of the &amp;quot;Central Eight&amp;quot;; Andrews &amp;amp; Bonta, 2010) and psychotic symptoms were independently associated with arrest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Transinstitutionalization Explain the Overrepresentation of People with Serious Mental Illnesses in the Criminal Justice System?</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-does-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-does-2011/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although there is broad consensus that people with serious mental illnesses (SMI) are overrepresented in correctional settings, there is less agreement about the policy trends that may have created this situation. Some researchers and policymakers posit a direct link between deinstitutionalization and increased rates of SMI in jails and prisons, a phenomenon described as transinstitutionalization. Others offer evidence that challenges this hypothesis and suggest that it may be a reductionist explanation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
