<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Aged on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/aged/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Aged on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/aged/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Immigration Policies and Mental Health Morbidity among Latinos: A State-Level Analysis</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-immigration-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-immigration-2017/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     RATIONALE: Despite abundant state-level policy activity in the U.S. related to immigration, no research has examined the mental health impact of the overall policy climate for Latinos, taking into account both inclusionary and exclusionary legislation. OBJECTIVE: To examine associations between the state-level policy climate related to immigration and mental health outcomes among Latinos. METHODS: We created a multi-sectoral policy climate index that included 14 policies in four domains (immigration, race/ethnicity, language, and agricultural worker protections).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unequal Depression for Equal Work? How the Wage Gap Explains Gendered Disparities in Mood Disorders</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/platt-unequal-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/platt-unequal-2016/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Mood disorders, such as depression and anxiety, are more prevalent among women than men. This disparity may be partially due to the effects of structural gender discrimination in the work force, which acts to perpetuate gender differences in opportunities and resources and may manifest as the gender wage gap. We sought to quantify and operationalize the wage gap in order to explain the gender disparity in depression and anxiety disorders, using data from a 2001-2002 US nationally representative survey of 22,581 working adults ages 30-65.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
