<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prevalence on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/prevalence/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Prevalence on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/prevalence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Joint Effects of Age, Period, and Cohort on Conduct Problems Among American Adolescents From 1991 Through 2015</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although arrest rates among juveniles have substantially decreased since the 1990s, US national trends in conduct problems are unknown. Population variation in conduct problems would imply changes in the social environment, which would include emergent or receding risk factors. In the present study, we separated age, period, and cohort effects on conduct problems using nationally representative surveys of 375,879 US students conducted annually (1991-2015). The summed score of 7 items measuring the frequency of conduct problems was the outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anxious? Depressed? You Might Be Suffering from Capitalism: Contradictory Class Locations and the Prevalence of Depression and Anxiety in the USA</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-anxious-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-anxious-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Despite a well-established social gradient for many mental disorders, there is evidence that individuals near the middle of the social hierarchy suffer higher rates of depression and anxiety than those at the top or bottom. Although prevailing indicators of socioeconomic status (SES) cannot detect or easily explain such patterns, relational theories of social class, which emphasise political-economic processes and dimensions of power, might. We test whether the relational construct of contradictory class location, which embodies aspects of both ownership and labour, can explain this nonlinear pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prevalence of Mental Illnesses in U.S. State Prisons: A Systematic Review</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-prevalence-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-prevalence-2014/</guid>
      <description>Absract     Objective: People with mental illnesses are understood to be overrepresented in the U.S. criminal justice system, and accurate prevalence estimates in corrections settings are crucial for planning and implementing preventive and diversionary policies and programs. Despite consistent scholarly attention to mental illness in corrections facilities, only two federal self-report surveys are typically cited, and they may not represent the extent of relevant data. This systematic review was conducted to develop a broader picture of mental illness prevalence in U.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
