<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mass incarceration on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/mass-incarceration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mass incarceration on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/tags/mass-incarceration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Photos &amp; Video Show NYPD Officers, Including Top Brass, Openly Flouting Mask Mandate • Gothamist</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/christopher-robbins-photos-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/christopher-robbins-photos-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>70% of Texas Prisoners Tested Have the Coronavirus. Experts Say It&#39;s Time for More Testing and Fewer Inmates. • The Texas Tribune</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/mccullough-70-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/mccullough-70-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One Month Later, No Sign of Respite at Jail in San Antonio • San Antonio Express-News</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/eaton-one-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/eaton-one-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grinis v. Spaulding • ACLU Massachusetts</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/noauthor-grinis-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/noauthor-grinis-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>County Jail Incarceration Rates and County Mortality Rates in the United States, 1987– 2016</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/kajeepeta-county-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/kajeepeta-county-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Objectives. To evaluate the relationship between changes in county jail incarceration rates and subsequent county mortality rates across the United States. Methods. We analyzed county jail incarceration rates from the Bureau of Justice Statistics from 1987 to 2016 for 1884 counties and mortality rates from the National Vital Statistics System. We fit 1-year-lagged quasi-Poisson 2-way fixed-effects models, controlling for unmeasured stable county characteristics, and measured time-varying confounders, including county poverty and crime rates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Disciplining Effect of Mass Incarceration on Labor Organization</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/reich-disciplining-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/reich-disciplining-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Previous research has described the criminal justice system as a “labor market institution.” In recent years, however, research on the relationship between the criminal justice system and the labor market has focused primarily on the negative impact of criminal justice involvement on an individual’s ability to find work postrelease. This article explores how workers’ exposure to the criminal justice system is related to labor organization—a labor market institution through which workers in the United States have secured benefits for themselves and that, structurally, has mitigated income inequality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exposure to Criminal Justice System Criminalizes Young People Further, Shows Study • Development Channel</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/noauthor-exposure-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/press/noauthor-exposure-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
