<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Peer-Reviewed Research on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</title>
    <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Peer-Reviewed Research on Critical Social Epidemiology Research Collaborative</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Structural sexism and Women&#39;s alcohol use in the United States, 1988–2016</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/mcketta-structural-sexism-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/mcketta-structural-sexism-2022/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Background Women&amp;rsquo;s alcohol consumption and binge drinking have increased concurrent with socio-economic gains and may be related to structural sexism. Methods We examined associations between structural sexism (state-level sex inequality in political/economic status), and alcohol outcomes among women in Monitoring the Future (N = 20,859) from 1988 to 2016 (ages 27–45 in 2016). We controlled for state and individual confounders and tested three mediators: depressive symptoms, restrictive alcohol norms, and college completion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wage theft and life expectancy inequities in the United States: A simulation study</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-wage-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-wage-2022/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Wage theft – employers not paying workers their legally entitled wages and benefits – costs workers billions of dollars annually. We tested whether preventing wage theft could increase U.S. life expectancy and decrease inequities therein. We obtained nationally representative estimates of the 2001–2014 association between income and expected age at death for 40-year-olds (40 plus life expectancy at age 40) compiled from tax and Social Security Administration records, and estimates of the burden of wage theft from several sources, including estimates regarding minimum-wage violations (not paying workers the minimum wage) developed from Current Population Survey data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The politics of depression: Diverging trends in internalizing symptoms among US adolescents by political beliefs</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/gimbrone-politics-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/gimbrone-politics-2022/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Adolescent internalizing symptoms (e.g. depressive affect) have increased over the past decade in the US, particularly among girls. The reasons for these increases are unclear. We hypothesize that increasing exposure to politicized events has contributed to these trends in adolescent internalizing symptoms, and that effects may be differential by political beliefs and sociodemographic characteristics. We analyzed nationally-representative data from 2005 to 2018 Monitoring the Future annual cross-sectional samples of 12th-grade students (N ​= ​86,138).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>School Health Predictors of the School-to-Prison Pipeline: Substance Use and Developmental Risk and Resilience Factors</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-school-health-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-school-health-2022/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Purpose: The purpose of the study is to establish prospective relationships among school mean levels of substance use, developmental risk and resilience factors, and school discipline. Methods: We linked 2003e2014 data from the California Healthy Kids Survey and the Civil Rights Data Collection, from more than 4,800 schools and 4,950,000 students. With lagged multilevel linear models, we estimated relationships among standardized school average levels of six substance use measures; eight developmental risk and resilience factors; and the prevalence of total discipline, out-of-school discipline, and police-involved discipline.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free agents or cogs in the machine? Classed, gendered, and racialized inequities in hazardous working conditions</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-cogs-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-cogs-2021/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Introduction:
Few epidemiologic studies have used relational social class measures based on control over productive assets and others&#39; labor to analyze inequities in health-affecting working conditions. Moreover, these studies have often neglected the gendered and racialized dimensions of class relations, dimensions which are essential to understanding population patterns of health inequities. Our study fills these gaps.
Methods:
Using data from the 2002–2018 U.S. General Social Survey, we assigned respondents to the worker, manager, petit bourgeois, or capitalist classes based on their supervisory authority and self-employment status.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Policing the pandemic: estimating spatial and racialized inequities in New York City police enforcement of COVID-19 mandates</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/kajeepeta-policing-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/kajeepeta-policing-2021/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     The use of policing to enforce public health guidelines has historically produced harmful consequences, and early evidence from the police enforcement of COVID-19 mandates suggested Black New Yorkers were disproportionately represented in arrests. The over-policing of Black and low-income neighborhoods during a pandemic risks increased transmission, potentially exacerbating existing health inequities. To assess racialized and class-based inequities in the enforcement of COVID-19 mandates at the ZIP-code-level, we conducted a retrospective spatial analysis of demographic factors and public health policing in New York City from 12 March–24 May 2020.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Litigation as a Structural Strategy for Addressing Bias-Based Bullying Among Youth</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-litigation-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-litigation-2021/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Homophobic bullying—which is motivated by actual or perceived sexual orientation—is a common experience among youth and is more strongly associated with adverse outcomes than bullying unrelated to bias. Yet current approaches to reducing homophobic bullying either lack empirical evidence or encounter significant obstacles. Thus, the field requires the identification of strategies that hold promise for reducing homophobic bullying.To examine whether litigation is associated with reductions in homophobic bullying.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criminogenic Risk Assessment: A Meta-Review and Critical Analysis</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2021/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     A vast body of research underlies the ascendancy of criminogenic risk assessment, which was developed to predict recidivism. It is unclear, however, whether the empirical evidence supports its expansion across the criminal legal system. This meta-review thus attempts to answer the following questions: 1) How well does criminogenic risk assessment differentiate people who are at high risk of recidivism from those at low risk of recidivism?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>US trends in binge drinking by gender, occupation, prestige, and work structure among adults in the midlife, 2006–2018</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/mcketta-binge-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/mcketta-binge-2021/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Background
Rates of binge drinking have nearly doubled among US women ages 30–49 since 2006. Employment influences alcohol use and varies by the prestige and structure (e.g., authority, autonomy, expertise) of one&amp;rsquo;s occupation.
Methods
We examined trends in binge drinking among adults ages 30–49 in the labor force in 2006–2018 National Health Interview Surveys (N = 108,981) by occupation, work prestige (General Social Survey&amp;rsquo;s occupational prestige score), work structure (occupational authority, autonomy, automation, expertise), and gender.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Association between County Jail Incarceration and Cause-Specific County Mortality in the USA, 1987– 2017: A Retrospective, Longitudinal Study</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/kajeepeta-association-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/kajeepeta-association-2021/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Background: Mass incarceration has collateral consequences for community health, which are reflected in county-level health indicators, including county mortality rates. County jail incarceration rates are associated with all-cause mortality rates in the USA. We assessed the causes of death that drive the relationship between county-level jail incarceration and mortality.
Methods: In this retrospective, longitudinal study, we assessed the association between county-level jail incarceration rates and county-level cause-specific mortality using county jail incarceration data (1987–2017) for 1094 counties in the USA obtained from the Vera Institute of Justice and cause-specific mortality data for individuals younger than 75 years in the total county population (1988–2018) obtained from the US National Vital Statistics System.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Serpent of Their Agonies&#34;: Exploitation As Structural Determinant of Mental Illness</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-serpent-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-serpent-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Background: Social stratification is a well-documented determinant of mental health. Traditional measures of stratification (e.g., socioeconomic status) reduce dynamic social processes to individual attributes downstream of mechanisms that generate stratification. In this study, we measure one process theorized to generate and reproduce social stratification—economic exploitation—and explore its association with mental health.
Methods: Data are from the 1983 to 2017 waves of the Panel Study of Income Dynamics, a nationally representative cohort study (base- line N = 3059).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting the Dots Between Mass Incarceration, Health Inequity, and Climate Change</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-connecting-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-connecting-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>County Jail Incarceration Rates and County Mortality Rates in the United States, 1987– 2016</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/kajeepeta-county-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/kajeepeta-county-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Objectives. To evaluate the relationship between changes in county jail incarceration rates and subsequent county mortality rates across the United States. Methods. We analyzed county jail incarceration rates from the Bureau of Justice Statistics from 1987 to 2016 for 1884 counties and mortality rates from the National Vital Statistics System. We fit 1-year-lagged quasi-Poisson 2-way fixed-effects models, controlling for unmeasured stable county characteristics, and measured time-varying confounders, including county poverty and crime rates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Sensitive Periods When Changes in Parenting and Peer Factors Are Associated with Changes in Adolescent Alcohol and Marijuana Use</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-identifying-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-identifying-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     There are well-established associations between parental/peer relationships and adolescent substance use, but few longitudinal studies have examined whether adolescents change their substance use in response to changes in their parents&#39; behavior or peer networks. We employ a within-person change approach to address two key questions: Are changes in parenting and peer factors associated with changes in adolescent marijuana and alcohol use? Are there sensitive periods when changes in parenting and peer factors are more strongly associated with changes in adolescent marijuana and alcohol use?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relational Social Class, Self-Rated Health, and Mortality in the United States</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-relational-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/eisenberg-guyot-relational-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Applying a relational class theory based on property ownership, authority, and credentials/skill, we analyzed the relationship between class, self-rated health (SRH), and mortality using the 1972–2016 General Social Survey. In a simple measure of class, we assigned respondents to worker, manager, petty bourgeois, or capitalist classes. In a complex measure, we subdivided workers (less-skilled/more-skilled), managers (low/high), and capitalists (small/large). Next, we estimated trends in class structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structural Stigma and All-Cause Mortality among Sexual Minorities: Differences by Sexual Behavior?</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-structural-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-structural-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Using updated data from the General Social Survey/National Death Index (GSS/NDI) study, we examined whether the relationship between structural stigma-measured by aggregating 4 items assessing prejudice towards homosexuality to the community level-and all-cause mortality is present among gay men/lesbian women. Our hypothesis is based on emerging evidence that indicators of structural stigma specific to homosexuality, such as those used in the GSS/NDI, uniquely predict health outcomes among this group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Disciplining Effect of Mass Incarceration on Labor Organization</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/reich-disciplining-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/reich-disciplining-2020/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Previous research has described the criminal justice system as a “labor market institution.” In recent years, however, research on the relationship between the criminal justice system and the labor market has focused primarily on the negative impact of criminal justice involvement on an individual’s ability to find work postrelease. This article explores how workers’ exposure to the criminal justice system is related to labor organization—a labor market institution through which workers in the United States have secured benefits for themselves and that, structurally, has mitigated income inequality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criminogenic or Criminalized? Testing an Assumption for Expanding Criminogenic Risk Assessment</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2019/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     OBJECTIVES: Proponents of criminogenic risk assessment have called for its widespread expansion throughout the criminal justice system. Its success in predicting recidivism is taken as evidence that criminogenic risks tap into the causes of criminal behavior, and that targeting these factors can reduce correctional supervision rates and even prevent crime. This study challenges these assertions, by testing the implicit assumption that populations in which recidivism risk factors were identified are interchangeable with populations experiencing the onset/duration of exposure to the criminal justice system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mental Illness, Drinking, and the Social Division and Structure of Labor in the United States: 2003-2015</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-mental-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-mental-2019/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     BACKGROUND: We draw on a relational theoretical perspective to investigate how the social division and structure of labor are associated with serious and moderate mental illness and binge and heavy drinking.
METHODS: The Panel Study of Income Dynamics and the Occupational Information Network were linked to explore how occupation, the productivity-to-pay gap, unemployment, the gendered division of domestic labor, and factor-analytic and theory-derived dimensions of work are related to mental illness and drinking outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Examination of Parental and Peer Influence on Substance Use and Criminal Offending During the Transition from Adolescence to Adulthood</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/beardslee-examination-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/beardslee-examination-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although peer behavior and parent-child-conflict have been associated with adolescent and young adults&#39; behavior, prior studies have not adequately controlled for selection effects and other confounders, or examined whether associations change across the transition to adulthood or by race. Using annual data from young men followed from 17-26, within-individual change models examined whether substance use or offending increased in the year after boys began affiliating with friends who engaged in substance use/offending and/or experienced increased parent-son-conflict.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can We Avoid Reductionism in Risk Reduction?</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-can-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-can-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Risk assessment and risk reduction have become increasingly central to criminal justice policy and practice in the last 25 years. Yet there remains a lack of consensus both on the theoretical and methodological foundations of risk and on its social and practical implications. Some proponents see risk assessment and reduction as solutions to the inefficiencies and injustices of contemporary mass incarceration. Some critics see actuarial risk as being partially responsible for mass incarceration, and warn that recent iterations will only reinscribe existing inequalities under a new guise of objectivity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joint Effects of Age, Period, and Cohort on Conduct Problems Among American Adolescents From 1991 Through 2015</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/keyes-joint-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although arrest rates among juveniles have substantially decreased since the 1990s, US national trends in conduct problems are unknown. Population variation in conduct problems would imply changes in the social environment, which would include emergent or receding risk factors. In the present study, we separated age, period, and cohort effects on conduct problems using nationally representative surveys of 375,879 US students conducted annually (1991-2015). The summed score of 7 items measuring the frequency of conduct problems was the outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Sequencing to Determine Patterns in Health and Work-Family Trajectories for U.S. Women, 1968-2013</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/mcketta-social-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/mcketta-social-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Background: Women&amp;rsquo;s social roles (partnership, parenthood, and worker status) are associated with health, with more roles being associated with lower mortality rates. Few studies have examined social roles using a lifecourse perspective to understand how changing role dynamics affect health over time. Sequence analysis is one analytic technique for examining social trajectories. Methods: Work-family trajectories were determined using social sequence analysis. We estimated mortality using age-standardized mortality rates and Poisson regression and examined the impact of personal income as a mediator.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immigration Policies and Mental Health Morbidity among Latinos: A State-Level Analysis</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-immigration-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/hatzenbuehler-immigration-2017/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     RATIONALE: Despite abundant state-level policy activity in the U.S. related to immigration, no research has examined the mental health impact of the overall policy climate for Latinos, taking into account both inclusionary and exclusionary legislation. OBJECTIVE: To examine associations between the state-level policy climate related to immigration and mental health outcomes among Latinos. METHODS: We created a multi-sectoral policy climate index that included 14 policies in four domains (immigration, race/ethnicity, language, and agricultural worker protections).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the &#34;Well-Defined Intervention Assumption&#34; Politically Conservative?</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/schwartz-is-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/schwartz-is-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unequal Depression for Equal Work? How the Wage Gap Explains Gendered Disparities in Mood Disorders</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/platt-unequal-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/platt-unequal-2016/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Mood disorders, such as depression and anxiety, are more prevalent among women than men. This disparity may be partially due to the effects of structural gender discrimination in the work force, which acts to perpetuate gender differences in opportunities and resources and may manifest as the gender wage gap. We sought to quantify and operationalize the wage gap in order to explain the gender disparity in depression and anxiety disorders, using data from a 2001-2002 US nationally representative survey of 22,581 working adults ages 30-65.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weighing the Evidence for Harm from Long-Term Treatment with Antipsychotic Medications: A Systematic Review</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/sohler-weighing-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/sohler-weighing-2016/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Research findings supporting the use of antipsychotic medication for acute treatment of schizophrenia are relatively consistent and undisputed. However, the rationale for recommending long-term antipsychotic medication treatment-the current standard of care treatment strategy-is unclear. A controversial hypothesis proposed recently suggests people with schizophrenia who are exposed to long-term treatment with antipsychotic medications have worse outcomes than people with schizophrenia who are not exposed to these medications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Psychopathology Matters Most: Identifying Sensitive Periods When within-Person Changes in Conduct, Affective, and Anxiety Problems Are Associated with Male Adolescent Substance Use</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/cerda-when-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/cerda-when-2016/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     BACKGROUND AND AIMS There is a documented link between common psychiatric disorders and substance use in adolescent males. This study addressed two key questions: (1) is there a within-person association between an increase in psychiatric problems and an increase in substance use among adolescent males and (2) are there sensitive periods during male adolescence when such associations are more evident? DESIGN Analysis of longitudinal data collected annually on boys selected randomly from schools based on a comprehensive public school enrollment list from the Pittsburgh Board of Education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anxious? Depressed? You Might Be Suffering from Capitalism: Contradictory Class Locations and the Prevalence of Depression and Anxiety in the USA</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-anxious-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-anxious-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Despite a well-established social gradient for many mental disorders, there is evidence that individuals near the middle of the social hierarchy suffer higher rates of depression and anxiety than those at the top or bottom. Although prevailing indicators of socioeconomic status (SES) cannot detect or easily explain such patterns, relational theories of social class, which emphasise political-economic processes and dimensions of power, might. We test whether the relational construct of contradictory class location, which embodies aspects of both ownership and labour, can explain this nonlinear pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criminogenic Factors, Psychotic Symptoms, and Incident Arrests among People with Serious Mental Illnesses under Intensive Outpatient Treatment</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-criminogenic-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although research robustly indicates that general or &amp;quot;criminogenic&amp;quot; factors predict various measures of recidivism, there is controversy about the extent to which these factors, versus untreated symptoms, lead to justice involvement for people with mental illnesses. Based on a sample of 183 people in intensive outpatient treatment followed for an average period of 34.5 months, the present study tested whether criminogenic factors (i.e., factor-analytically derived proxies of some of the &amp;quot;Central Eight&amp;quot;; Andrews &amp;amp; Bonta, 2010) and psychotic symptoms were independently associated with arrest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Class and Mental Health: Testing Exploitation as a Relational Determinant of Depression</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/muntaner-social-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/muntaner-social-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     This study tests whether social class exploitation operates as a relational mechanism that generates mental health inequalities in the nursing home industry. We ask, does social class exploitation (i.e., the acquisition of economic benefits from the labor of those who are dominated) have a systematic and predictable impact on depression among nursing assistants? Using cross-sectional data from 868 nursing assistants employed in 50 nursing homes in three U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Decades of Neo-Marxist Class Analysis and Health Inequalities: A Critical Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/muntaner-two-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/muntaner-two-2015/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Most population health researchers conceptualize social class as a set of attributes and material conditions of life of individuals. The empiricist tradition of &amp;lsquo;class as an individual attribute&amp;rsquo; equates class to an &amp;lsquo;observation&amp;rsquo;, precluding the investigation of unobservable social mechanisms. Another consequence of this view of social class is that it cannot be conceptualized, measured, or intervened upon at the meso- or macro levels, being reduced to a personal attribute.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prevalence of Mental Illnesses in U.S. State Prisons: A Systematic Review</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-prevalence-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-prevalence-2014/</guid>
      <description>Absract     Objective: People with mental illnesses are understood to be overrepresented in the U.S. criminal justice system, and accurate prevalence estimates in corrections settings are crucial for planning and implementing preventive and diversionary policies and programs. Despite consistent scholarly attention to mental illness in corrections facilities, only two federal self-report surveys are typically cited, and they may not represent the extent of relevant data. This systematic review was conducted to develop a broader picture of mental illness prevalence in U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Substance Use Disorders,</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-substance-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-substance-2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Determine the Prevalence of Mental Illnesses in Jails and Prisons?</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-why-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-why-2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Racial Disparities in The Brief Jail Mental Health Screen</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-exploring-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-exploring-2012/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     The authors analyzed validation data from the Brief Jail Mental Health Screen (BJMHS) to determine whether race predicted screening results and if such a prediction was driven by particular screen items. A total of 22,000 individuals entering five jails over two 8-month periods were screened. The authors constructed binary logistic regression models to assess the impact of race on screening positive and endorsing particular items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Transinstitutionalization Explain the Overrepresentation of People with Serious Mental Illnesses in the Criminal Justice System?</title>
      <link>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-does-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://criticalsocialepi.org/research/prins-does-2011/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Although there is broad consensus that people with serious mental illnesses (SMI) are overrepresented in correctional settings, there is less agreement about the policy trends that may have created this situation. Some researchers and policymakers posit a direct link between deinstitutionalization and increased rates of SMI in jails and prisons, a phenomenon described as transinstitutionalization. Others offer evidence that challenges this hypothesis and suggest that it may be a reductionist explanation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
